This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
This is Nate Black for Software
Engineering Radio.
My guest today is Jean-Denis Greze.
Jean-Denis is head of engineering at
Plaid, the technology company giving
developers access to the financial
system and the tools to build many of
the most influential applications and
services such as those provided by
PayPal, Venmo, Coinbase, Robinhood, and
many others.
Prior to joining Plaid, Jean-Denis was
director of engineering at Dropbox,
where he led the growth, identity,
notifications, paper, and payments
teams.
Prior to Dropbox, Jean-Denis worked in
fintech in New York and has CS degrees
from Columbia, as well as a JD from
Harvard Law School.
Jean-Denis, welcome to Software
Engineering Radio.
Cool. Thanks so much for having me,
Nate.
It's great to have you.
Jean-Denis,
you have a unique perspective on the the
phase of growth that startups face when
they already have some existing products
and they're trying to figure out how to
get from where they are to building new
products while
keeping everything happy as far as
customer expectations go. You have
referred to this concept as engineering
maturity. Can we give a quick definition
about what engineering maturity is?
Yeah, for sure. So, everyone's dream is
to have an organization which has the
capabilities and skills that are
necessary to achieve kind of its goals,
right? It's business goals to to to meet
like whatever customer demand that it
has. And I think
what's most interesting when you're
working at a
you know, at a company that's fast
growing is you will never have the
adequate maturity relative to the
problems that you have because, you
know, demand and growth is forcing you
to scale so quickly. And when I say
scale, I mean both scale obviously your
software and and the product that you're
building, but also not the org itself,
you know, and that could be hiring, it
could be just becoming having better
processes for how you operate as a
group. And um what's been interesting to
me is like if
if you talk to a lot of heads of
engineering or or or managers in
different orgs, they're all struggling
with the idea of like, "Hey, how do I
how do I level up my org? How do I level
up my team?" But there's no like
consistent way to think about it. You
know, most often people look at the
thing that's the most broken at their
company and then they're like, "Okay,
well, you know, this is broken. This
this is not working like our the way we
interview people is not scaling or the
way we kind of do on-calls isn't working
anymore or whatnot." They look at this
one problem and then they you know,
they're smart people, so they they they
address it, right? They either talk to
companies that are quote more mature and
that have figured out how to do that.
They get a bunch of input and then they,
you know, they do organizational changes
to address the problem. And I think
that's that's great, but the the problem
with it is it it leaves you in more of a
responsive mode because what you're what
you have to do is you have to wait for
things to break to start to think about
the solution. And and you know, I I
think the the common solution to that is
actually to generally hire kind of a a
head of engineering or a VP of
engineering that has seen the growth
before. The idea being that, you know,
because they've seen like a larger
successful organization run, they
understand the delta between where you
are as a startup today and where you
need to be tomorrow to be successful.
And I think that's like a it's a very
adequate solution, but it's a very like
person-centric solution to the problem.
You know, and as an engineer you I
always think of of you you don't want a
bus factor, right? You don't you don't
want problems that just rely on a
specific kind of person for you to be
successful. So, you know, over over the
past, you know, couple of years that
I've seen kind of this happen, you know,
when I was when I was at Dropbox and now
as we were kind of, you know, growing
very fast at at Plaid and kind of
re-encountering some of these same
lessons, I've been thinking about how do
we how do we define a framework for both
like defining and leveling up an
organization's level of quote
engineering maturity.
I see. So,
one approach would be
to just address problems in an ad hoc
fashion and you're looking for something
more holistic.
But when you say like you have a
framework,
you want a framework for leveling up, it
kind of sounds like
some kind of gamification system. Is it
Is something like that or something
else?
I think I mean I think of it more as a
roadmap, although I think if you do it
right, it'll actually lead to the
organization naturally wanting to level
up. And and then in that sense you you
you would benefit from kind of a a
gamification angle to it. So, I think
like actually a really good a really
easy way to think about this is and I'm
sure most people in the audience will be
familiar with this if they work at at
companies of any size. It's It's levels,
right? And titles that are given to
employees. So, at most companies, right,
you when you join, you're you're leveled
as an engineer or maybe you're like
level one, right? And then after 18
months, if you achieve some objective
set of things, then you might get a
promotion to level two. And then you
know, after another like two years of
work, you might become L3. And then at
some point, you might become a senior
engineer or a staff engineer or you
know, maybe a principal engineer. And
so, you know, all these companies, they
have they have a level map and with an
objective set of criteria of what they
expect somebody to do well in order to
get to the next level.
Right, and that's like pretty standard
in the industry. I'm talking about
building something equivalent kind of at
the org level
and at the system level. So, that the
org as a whole realizes, "Hey, as an
org, we're like a level two org because
there's these capabilities that we
haven't developed yet." and like the
natural evolution for us is to start to
develop those capabilities
you know before things break so much,
right?
And I think you you can actually use
this approach like pretty broadly,
right? You can apply it at the at the
individual level and and most companies
do that. You can apply it at the org
level which is basically what I want to
argue for in the podcast, but you can
also apply it you know at the team level
like even within you know any kind of
engineering driven company you'll have
different teams that will have different
levels of of maturity, right? Some teams
already you know they have a very well
developed on-call, they have a a way to
get inputs from for product requirements
from a number of teams, they have a way
to they have a like very set process for
you know getting that into like a great
product and so on and so forth. But
there might be other teams that for
whatever reason you spun them up later
and they haven't had time to develop
that full skill set. And so then if you
think about it at the team level it
gives an incentive actually for managers
to want to like objectively like level
up their team, right? Um because they
know what they have to do to get the
next level of capabilities. And then it
serves another function which is if
other people in the org understand have
like a framework mentally for
understanding how mature different parts
of your engineering kind of function are
then that means they can have like they
can set the right set of expectations
about what they can expect from someone
else within the company. And I think
that part's really important because I
think what you any fast growing
engineering org where they'll have
they'll experience times where some
teams are like way ahead of the game
relatively speaking and and others are
kind of catching up and struggling,
right? So you might have
a really really strong product
engineering team that's like that's like
running really well, but for whatever
reason you didn't have the time to
invest enough in platform and your SRE
team. And so SRE relatively speaking
just doesn't is not yet operating at the
level of product. And like how do you
realize in that in a way that's not
blaming and where kind of SRE realizes
hey, this is the next set of things we
need to like pick up on if we're going
to be able to support the rest of
engineering really successfully."
When I think about levels that
individuals would have, it makes sense
that I would expect a senior engineer or
architect or principal, whatever their
title happen to be, to have a higher
level of maturity and capability than a
junior engineer.
And you're saying extend that to the
team level so that the right
expectations would be there
between teams and kind of
make things more visible.
So, right, the key here, right, it's
everything is evolutionary, right? You
you you're looking at lots of small
improvements across many dimensions and
over time you just you ramp up the bar,
so to speak. So, if you think about a
team that owns a number of systems, the
lowest level of of maturity for that
team might be their new on-call
processes. Like all operations are
totally manual and ad hoc. Whenever
something goes goes wrong, there's no
understanding of like the failure domain
for the system. Like there's no
understanding of of like the range of
things that should that could cause that
system not to operate at the desired
level anymore. You might have no you've
never done disaster recovery of any
sort. So, there's like a long list of
things that you're going to be defined
in for the level level one team just
doesn't do anything well.
And then you might level up a couple
levels. So, you might say, "Okay, where
do you want to go to next?" So, you
might be able to go for on-call. Maybe
now we have some on-call support. Maybe
you have daytime on-call. Instead of all
operations being manual and ad hoc, you
have playbooks for 50% of the incidents
that happen during these like roughly
defined kind of on-call periods. The
team is only spending less than 30% of
its time keeping the systems up. You've
done one disaster recovery plan in the
last 12 months. Right? So, some Now
we've taken everything and we've just
been like, "Hey, we've defined these
these things. Now we're like one level
up. It's a little better." And then you
might look at it like a really mature
team and then you might say it is going
to look totally different. It's going to
be we have 20 24/7 on-call support. All
alerts that ever happened are remediated
automatically, meaning like without any
human interference
or any any like
human helping it along. You might say
you're spending less than 15% of your
time keeping the system up. You might
have a list of every failure domain that
could potentially happen to the system,
meaning whenever something goes wrong,
it's something that you were expecting
potentially to go wrong. Not only have
you done regular disaster recovery plan,
but you have you've done kind of scale
testing in place that mimics like real
traffic. And then finally, you have
clear SLAs that are defined and that
you've met for the past quarter, right?
So now we're talking about Right now
we're talking about a a team that if it
if it has done all these things, right?
It can it can deliver a service like at
a really high level to its customers.
And that wouldn't even be the ultimate
right level, like the the top level
actually for a system is where you're
spending zero time to keep it up. You
have you have 24/7 on-call, but you
haven't actually needed it for at least
a quarter. Like every alert is auto
remediated. You don't even have a
roadmap for the system anymore because
it doesn't need any improvements. It it
perfectly meets like the the needs that
the businesses has out of that system
for the next like 12 or 24 months,
right? And that's like that's the dream.
That's where we're all trying to get to,
but basically almost never do. So you
define these levels and and here I've
gone through like three or four, but you
might really have like, you know, seven
to 10. And and it's objective and it's
it's a set of things that like literally
every team in within your organization
is striving to improve at. And thus it
provides a really clear roadmap for like
where and how much time you need to
invest in foundation to to get the next
level. And and you kind of set
expectations. You say, "We expect every
6 months or so for a team to like up
level by one." And so, you know, that
way you have an understanding, you know,
if you have eight levels and every 6
months you you expect people to up
level, you like it takes 4 years, right?
But at least everything is on a path
over 4 years to get to that perfect
maturity. And everyone has a clear
understanding of like what it takes to
to step up.
As you were describing
the process of the team leveling up and
the system going more towards stability,
it sounds also like the the the product
itself is evolving. So, it seems that
the maturity of the team might be tied
in some way to the life cycle of the
product or maybe the the company itself.
Is there a relationship there? How is
the maturity of the team related to
the maturity or the life cycle of the
product?
It's It's a good question. I mean, the
the I think the obvious answer is if you
have a a product that's that doesn't
change much in term of its user
requirements, then it's like much easier
to move up the hierarchy than if you
have one that's changing all the time,
meaning, you know, you need to you need
to like add capabilities to it all the
time. And I think that's the real
struggle for any fast-growing company
between like really moving fast, which
by very definition introduces technical
debt and organizational debt, you know,
or or or or addressing that debt and
thus moving slower. There's no like
There's really no easy answer to that. I
just think as you grow as an org, right?
Your customers depend on you more. And
so, regardless of your ability to move
fast on the on the product end and
develop new things, you there's a
natural ratcheting up of people's
expectations of like your uptime and and
the quality of the service that you
provide. And just because of that, you
you have to naturally be able to to move
up um the ladder. Yes, that you know,
that does align with the maturity of the
product, but I don't think that's
necessary. Right? You might build
something new for your customers, but
your customers are not expecting you to
even when you launch something new to
have to have a higher quality bar, and
they're not going to let you go back to
like yoloing everything, right? Or if
you do, they're just not going to have
any trust in that product and and you
know, they're not going to use it. And I
think you know, the the example that I
just gave you what was very focused
actually on like a system maturity. Like
the team maturity version is is will be
on software things. It'll be like a
beginner team. It's like everyone is a
the bus factor is is one for like every
system.
Team meetings
are basically the manager telling
everybody what to do, but there's no
real room for for discussion. You might
be 40% green on your sprint goals sprint
over sprints. Like 10% of projects are
delivered on time, right? Like like a
team might might look like that. And
then a really mature team it won't be
focused on the product so much. It will
be like there's a culture of constant
feedback or the team is constantly
creating ideas and prioritizing new
projects versus relying on something
clunky like quarterly or semi-annual
planning. Every engineer has a career
develop- career development plan that
kind of stretches that that determines
what they need to do to be like to get
to the next level or to improve their
skill set. You're 90% green on sprint
goals. Like team meetings are
collaborative and everybody's voice
feels heard, right? Like you know, you
can take the the leveling approach and
you can you can use it at many different
levels of abstraction, right? Or you
could even abstract it to an org as a
whole, which is you know, you have like
a consistent objective interview process
that is blind to various diversity
limiters. You have an onboarding process
that leads to people like understanding
not just like the work, but like the the
of the team and so on and so forth,
Right, you can you can apply the
leveling approach to just about anything
you want. And I think that's very, very
powerful because it aligns it it makes
it clear to everybody in the org what
you're striving for.
It sounded like some of the metrics that
you had like on call percentage were
related to the team, but you said it's
system level. So,
is that then
potentially cross team at a company
level or is it you break it down by
product where or how do you actually
apply that?
Well, I think the systems I mean I
generally owned within a team, so that's
even like sub within the team. Right,
you might have a system where you're not
you're not able to auto remediate, you
know, 50% of alerts.
But that team might also own another
system where that's like easily doable.
That's that's more like the distinction
that I meant. I think ideally this works
really well in if it overlaps with your
management structure, so with your team
structure and so on and so forth. It's I
haven't Actually, it's a it's a good
question. It's not one I've considered
before which is like you you could
probably build a framework that applies
across functions, right? It applies not
just to engineering, but to product or
it doesn't it just apply to one team,
but it it
it applies to multiple teams that are
working together towards a common goal.
I haven't done that because I find like
it's pretty easy to apply at the team
level cuz you just need right if you get
all the managers and and and the org as
a whole to like agree on the basic
principles, then it just kind of takes
care of itself and then each team
figures out what they need to do to get
the next level and you just sit back and
watch it happen. Whereas I think if it
works across like organizational layers,
I could see the coordination being
difficult more difficult, but honestly
that's probably worth trying.
I was thinking about systems being
operated maybe by
operations team and also a
separate engineering team, but maybe the
the assumption your next example is that
there's a devops approach where the team
is owning the entire product from end to
end, including like the delivery and and
operations. So, in other words, this
example or or maybe the approach might
be a really good fit for that that
style.
Yeah, you make a good point. I'm It's
funny cuz you say that like I have and
I'm very much based on how we operate
here at Pod. Like I very much have this
every engineer is also an SRE kind of
mentality. But for sure, like if you if
you break that up and you you have a
more kind of classical like SRE DevOps
like split between SRE DevOps and kind
of app developers themselves,
you you you might not be able to take
things like the SLA and make it part of
like a broad definition of engineering
maturity. Although you most certainly
would want to have it for your SRE and
DevOps team. I I think, you know, the
framework obviously, like different
teams, right, need different things,
have different requirements. So, I think
the strength comes from the
commonalities, like basing it on the
commonalities. I don't think that's
that's orthogonal to like having some
places have like a little bit of a
different framework. The reason I I
focus on the commonalities is just there
are enough and it really helps align
like your everyone on your on your teams
to try strive for the same things,
right? Now, obviously, if you build the
wrong framework, by the way, if you have
the if you have the wrong kind of levels
or you you have the wrong things in
there you put too much pressure on
people to move up too fast, right,
relative to the needs of the business,
you're also going to get in lots of
trouble, right? This is The issue with
all frameworks is that, you know, they
they're they're the right framework also
that are not for your business needs and
that's something that you should pay
attention to, right?
Yeah, that that brings up a a point I
wanted to talk about about when it makes
sense to invest in maturity because
uh maturity might be something that's
expensive to implement. You might be
searching for product market fit. If
it's early
or you might be at another level of
maturity as you just mentioned where it
doesn't make sense to invest anymore.
So, could could you talk about that what
point does it make sense to invest in
this area?
That question and the like how much to
how much to move fast versus reduce
technical debt or the you know, these
are like the foundational questions and
they're the reason why
I think a lot of engineers get get get
have a lot of job security and and and
are are compensated very well for their
work cuz they're they're hard questions
and if there was an easy answer, well,
God, we would all benefit from it. I I
think the there are a couple of things I
think that are that are really important
is like my experience is in is in
growing teams that have already reached
product market fit. So, if you're not in
product market fit land and you're
really iterating really really quickly
like I don't think any of this matters
to be frank.
There's a depending on what world you're
in, there's probably a baseline around
operations uptime, like I don't know,
two or three nines and around security
that has to be met for sure. But, you
know, before you get to product market
fit, you're very small and and
everyone's on the same page. You're team
of like 20 to 30 people at most. It
doesn't it doesn't matter a ton. I think
as soon as you have product market fit
and a set of customers that are your
your ARR is like a million or whatnot
and you have customers that rely on you
day-to-day to to get their work done. I
think you have to start thinking about
this. And I think the the great thing
about the framework is it forces you to
think about where you are now and where
do you need to be tomorrow or like
what's it in the future at some point.
And then
then the decision for you is pretty
easy, right? Then then I mean, it's
pretty easy. It's hard, but like then
you know what to focus you know what you
would have to do to be more mature. You
kind of understand what the next level
looks like. So, you can estimate how
much of an investment that is and you
can weigh that against the need for like
product requirements to move forward.
Now, what I've seen in practice at most
companies is that if you move up too
slowly in maturity, at some point,
there's a day of reckoning where you you
have to pay down. And and sometimes I've
I've seen startups do this, right? I've
seen startups have to like literally not
release features for 6 months because
there's something somewhere that is like
so bad and so gnarly that that they have
to address it. I've seen startups
basically ignore like the fairness of
their recruiting process for too long
and then wake up and have very
unbalanced teams in terms of either like
seniority or the the backgrounds of
people on the team and that can take
like years to fix. And it'll hurt your
ability to recruit. It'll hurt like your
internal like your culture. So, there's
there's there's all these things that
can definitely go bad and there's a
bunch of companies where it's gone bad.
And like my the my recommendation is
like you have like you have to be aware
and self-conscious about these tradeoffs
that you make along the way. And I think
the the real like
where you're kind of asking me is like
where when does
maturity matter? But you're also asking
me a little bit like what is immaturity,
right? And I think for me immaturity is
actually not having every team be level
one. Like that's not immaturity.
Immaturity is actually not even thinking
about it and not having a systemic way
to think about it to think about when
you should invest in it and being just
reactive to problems, right? Cuz by the
like by the time a problem hits you on
anything like recruiting or your
internal culture or the scalability of
your systems or whether you've promoted
the right people to managers, like by
the by the time it hits you, it's not
going to be when you just have one
manager that's bad or when you've had
like a couple of tough recruits. It's
when things are really really broken.
And by then, you're just in for a world
of pain. And there's plenty of companies
out there that have they've had to deal
with that and they've still been
successful in the end. So, I'm in no way
saying this is a difference between like
total failure and success. I'm just
saying you're losing velocity. You're
not being as like efficient as you could
be because you're not being systematic
as to how you think about these things.
And you know,
that's the that's the reason why every
fast growing company wants to hire
people who've done it before,
right? Cuz
cuz everyone knows there's like ways you
can kind of shoot yourself in the foot
and and then you're still walking,
you're limping, right? But you're not
sprinting anymore. And I think if you
think about this along the way, you can
you can see you can move pretty fast all
the way through.
That's a real chicken and egg problem if
you haven't seen it before and haven't
dealt with it. That's
I I think that's a situation where
you know, how do you begin? Can we go
back to
an example where you were in that
situation and you hadn't experienced the
level of growth or maturity and like
how did you how did you get past it?
Actually, really I'm just asking for any
any example where
you hadn't had the necessary level of
maturity, you felt some pain and needed
to to get to that level.
One area for me that that's very
interesting is the state of a developer
environment at a at a company. Dev
developer like your dev end, right?
You're like your VM, whatever you're
using to like locally develop. What's
interesting about it is not There's
plenty of like literature and thinking
about like, "Hey, this is what a great
dev end looks like." From the
perspective of the SRE or platform team
that's kind of creating that building
block for every engineer to work on a
But I think the the harder question is
how much should every cuz every every
team is building a service, right? So
every team has to make sure like their
tests have coverage, that their tests
are fast, that they run in the dev end
just like they do in production. There's
like you have this thing that has a
dependency on every every team in your
org. And and one thing that's
interesting is Dropbox is great It's a
great company. Many things are great.
When I joined, you know, we were like 90
engineers, is a little over 200 people
total.
The dev end was not was not in a good
place. And giving a lot of credits to
the the CTO at the time and and and VP
of engineering is they realized that and
and they invested a lot in getting it
into a good place. And the way they did
that was by hiring people
who'd seen it done well before, which is
great. Unfortunately, you know, when I
joined Plaid, that left me in a weird
place because I was like, well, I know
what to do. I know what to do if it's
ever really broken and I know what kind
of people I have to go hire to do it,
but those people are like way overkill
for what you need when you're a 20 per
20 engineer company. I joined Plaid two
two years ago, we were 20 engineers,
we're 70 today. So we have like we we
we've had a lot of good growth, but like
at 20, we didn't need like a world
expert on on on what your developer
environment should look like. And
frankly, I was like I also didn't have I
didn't have a good framework for how you
get from like where we were at the time
to that perfect world that Dropbox have
actually got to when it was like 400
engineers. I had just no had no road map
for it. So then, you know, the only
thing you can do is talk to people
who've done it before
at a number of other companies. It's
it's either that or hire someone who's
actually like seen through it, but I
didn't think I could find just that
right profile. So then you just
you know, you you pick up the Rolodex.
It's like it's like the non-recruiting
version of recruiting because uh
it's just as hard to get people to want
to meet with you, but you know, you you
go and you go talk to a bunch of people
and you're like, okay, these companies
are companies that have an amazing
developer experience like internally.
They've just they've just built that
well. How did they get there? Let's just
go talk to them, you know, find like the
the manager over there SRE team SRE team
at the time. It may not be the person
that's now working at the company
working on that, right? It might have
been the person that was working at the
time. Find them, put them in touch with
people on your team that are going to
work on that problem, have them spend a
bunch of time together, and just try to
like suck the best practices from them.
And the truth is actually like people in
Silicon Valley are very very If you can
get their time, which is hard, but
they're very very generous with the
information sharing. Like no one thinks
of like their developer environment as a
true big competitive advantage. It
actually kind of is, right? It cuz it
affects your overall velocity. But given
these are mature companies, they don't
see themselves as like competing with
like a younger startup like we were at
the time, they'll make time for you. You
get the learnings. And then from that,
then you you build kind of a a maturity
framework for that thing where you're
like, "Okay, well this is where we are,
this is where we need to get. Here steps
in between that we're okay with, and
this is a rough timeline for how we want
to do it." So that's a very like
software specific process, but the part
that was interesting to me is not is not
like how do you build a great great dev
VM, it's how do you how do you
incentivize other teams within the org,
all the teams that are building services
on top of the VM, to like mark their
services well, to make sure their test
coverage is really high. Now, to do all
of those things, it can be painful. Like
does it have to come from top down? Is
there a way you can provide visibility
into those stats so that they want to do
it on their own? And so on and so forth.
And I'm not sure the answer we got to
that is necessarily the best answer, but
just just thinking about it and talking
about it and and being like thoughtful
about it not just as a software problem
but as an org-wide problem, I think
makes a world of difference.
Okay, so you're you're on a journey
right now. You're not at the level of
400 engineers like you were at Dropbox.
You were you've grown from 20 to 70. And
as you try to get to 400, what are some
of the the goals or the steps that
you're taking?
I think we're ahead of the curve,
frankly, for
all of the main kind of verticals that I
think about as part of the maturity
framework. So I think for example, like
our recruiting practices in terms of the
the interview questions and how we
develop new interview questions, how we
do feedback, how we run debriefs, the
parts being really honest with ourselves
about the parts of of the interview
process that are really objective, those
where there's more potential for
subjective bias.
Uh training new interviewers, all that.
Like for the interviewing dimension, I
feel like really, really good about. I
feel so good about it that I think we're
like we can probably grow for 24 months
and it'll naturally adapt to handle
issues, right? We have like a an a
committee of engineers that are
responsible for a lot of those things.
And they care about it like I don't need
to get involved at all. It's It's as
good to It's as high maturity as you
could have for our size company. So,
there's a lot There's things like that
that I'm really, really happy about.
Right now, I think
top of mind
personally for me is
our ability to
meld in ad hoc work in addition to
what we plan for quarterly. And I think
I mentioned that a little bit earlier. I
was talking about constant
prioritization versus using I said
something clunky like quarterly or
bi-annual planning. So, I In my view of
engineering maturity, there's like
there's a point where everybody knows
what's happening and you're totally ad
hoc and you don't even have sprints or
quarterly planning and that works really
well. And then at some point,
coordination breaks down, right? And so
hopefully before that, you have sprints
and some kind of either quarterly or six
week or monthly, whatever works for your
company, cycle where teams coordinate
and you realize dependencies and you set
goals that are measurable and whatnot.
And I think we we did that transition
super well. And well, super well. We did
it and I think we got eventually to a
point that was super good. Mhm.
Quarterly planning is always painful.
The next The next step for us is to get
to a point where you don't really need
to do quarterly planning because teams
are constantly planning and prioritizing
and you're always writing like one-pager
proposals for projects. You're always
talking to customers and other teams and
getting their input. You have you've
gone to a point where like everything's
kind of flowing naturally and you don't
need to force a timeline on people. So,
that's like probably That's probably the
area where I feel we need to we have the
most room for improvement
on on on on the maturity map and I'm
pretty
pretty excited about driving that
forward. The next ones I mean the next
one's not that interesting but we we've
operated really well actually without
levels until today but there's lots of
issues with not having levels that I
think we're starting to kind of bump our
head into so I think that's like another
area for improvement in the next 12
months. Like we have leveling but it's
not it's not as like public and clear as
it could be. And then the third area
this is not in the maturity framework
that I have for for for pod and it's
something that I don't really know what
to do with right now and that it's
something I have a lot of questions
about. It's how we enable
Here's Here's an area that I There's
like an engineer that has an idea for
something great. It's not planned or
anything like that. They spend like two
days here or there like implementing a
V0 of it and then it turns out to be
awesome and you have to figure out how
to make it part of the org. Like how do
you go from that little internal MVP to
something real? I think we have we we we
we have that happen but we're not really
sure like how to like how to systemize
that practice so that more people do it
and I I think it goes it goes back to
the idea of like how do you reward like
creativity individual people on the team
outside of any like organized software
engineering process and that's something
that small companies are really good at
and so I wonder if we can keep that
moving forward cuz I see I'm afraid a
little bit less of it is happening as
we've grown. And maybe I'm wrong about
that one. Maybe it's actually not
something that's compatible with a
larger org cuz I haven't quite seen it
done well but I really want it to be so
I'm going to try to figure out if
there's a way to do that.
There is seems to be a bit of tension
there. You on one hand you want things
to be predictable, repeatable, reliable
but you want to leave some room for
creativity and for unplanned things to
spontaneously happen and be able to make
a new product that comes out of the
engineer or teams creative impulses.
It may seem like tension. I think for me
it's I view it more as like how do you
keep this part of the special sauce? How
do you keep it as as you grow? And the
reason why it's hard, so every
everything else, you know, I'm I'm in
when I talked about how we're
interviewing is in a good place and then
like all that stuff that's like
framework-tized, like I we have that.
We've got that. I mean, we can mess it
up, but we've we've got it. This is
something I don't have a good mental
model for and probably not a blog post
for me to talk about but maybe for
someone who's figured out how to do it,
but like maybe you you talk about it as
like it's the it's the Google 20% time
done right, right? And I say done right
because it it worked for a while at
Google and then it just didn't work,
right? And then they kind of got rid of
it. Like how do you how do you keep that
that early magic for a company that gets
bigger? I don't have an answer. And I
don't think it's a today problem for
Plaid cuz we're still pretty small, uh
but it it'll be a problem maybe in a
year or 2 years or 3 years and I'd love
to avoid it. And there I don't have I
actually don't even have a role model
that I think does it really well. I
can't think of a company that got that
super right that's like thousands of
people. If I did, I would go talk to
them.
Okay, so the leveling system
can do a lot of things, but maybe there
are some limitations or at least some
areas where you haven't applied it yet,
like in this uh 20% time uh example.
But we did talk about the success you
had in apply applying it to recruiting,
team dynamics, like feedback, and those
sorts of things.
You said it at the organizational level
it applies to leveling. Uh what are some
other areas that uh that your framework
does apply to?
Individual leveling, team leveling,
system like a software system maturity,
and the org as a whole. Like those are
the things that I've applied to
uh applied it to.
It works best when it's something that's
repeatable across different units within
your team. Like, it doesn't make a whole
lot of sense for maybe like Plaid as a
whole cuz we don't know what the future
of the company is going to be, right?
Like, that's ad hoc. Like, product
strategy and the challenges ahead by
like, there's no maturity framework for
that. It's just It's just that's That's
what the founders are for, right?
That's, you know, they're They're there
to help guide the strategy and make the
right choices for us and it's tough and,
you know, you're bought into what they
can do. So, I think the the framework
doesn't work at all in things that
haven't been done many times before. And
actually, some of its Some of its
biggest weaknesses, I think, are when
the the people you talk to to build the
framework about what better looks like,
when their solutions don't actually
aren't actually long-term sustainable
solutions is another like big failure of
it. And this is like one of my great
fears with Silicon Valley right now,
which is like, everyone's emulating a
company that's basically like a year and
a half to 2 years older than they are.
But like, it's not like those are
stable, long-lived businesses that have
figured out the best practices either,
right? It's like a It's like failed
evolution where you're like, copying
gene patterns before natural selection
has been able to take its course. So,
that's one of the things that that
scares me about it. You know, other
things that it's not good at or it has
other It has a bunch of failure modes.
Like, one failure mode is is like, going
up too fast. We were talking You were
talking before about like, you know,
going too slow. You know, not being able
to put enough time into like, improving
the maturity. I think there's another
part of it where you're like, way too
mature and set in stone for kind of the
kind of business that you have and the
uncertainty that you're faced. And so
then you're like, over-invest in Like,
say you could over-invest in recruiting
a certain kind of candidate and then you
wake up one day and you actually need
You need like, a totally different
interviewing process, right? And like,
all your culture is now like, aimed at
interviewing a certain kind of person.
You don't know what to do about that.
So, these are all judgment calls, right?
And that's As I was saying before,
that's why we're well
well compensated cuz it's it's not as
easy as a science.
Was there specific situation where you
over-invested in one area of maturity
that you had to scale back?
I think I have a fear of doing it almost
all the time. That's the way I would
word that. I don't think I've It's a
little bit difficult to identify, right?
Because it just cuz seems things seem
like they're working really well when
you over-invest. So, if anything, I I
think I try to You know, I was talking
about like you you don't want to wait
until the big breakage because then it's
too late. But, I think the the best
thing is you look for the tiniest
breakage and that that that forces you
to take like one step up the ladder.
That's I think more my approach how I
avoid over-investing.
Okay. What are the signals that you look
for that you may, you know, see some
problems down the road and you you
you've said, "Okay, this is an area
where I do need to invest."
I It's honestly it's really it's really
situation specific. So, here, like so
you want you want to have really good
managers, right? And you want your
managers to care about their people and
you want them to have the tools that
they need to to do their job very well.
And so, you know, if you're like really
mature org, you have like quarterly
training for your managers and you've
organized like kind of reading group
kind of equivalents where managers can
share information. You have all this
stuff that's happening, right? And when
you're my size, I was like, "Oh, we're
we're good place."
Got an external coach for all of my YMs.
I have like a basic setup for like how
we do off-sites, share information. I'm
encouraging like a few information flows
between all YMs so they kind of know how
others are solving problems. And I I
thought that was really good and I
thought I thought that was in a good
place. And then I started seeing a
couple people asking me questions that
I'd assumed they should already know how
to do. Like I would assume that they've
kind of self-educated to that to to
knowing how to solve that kind of
problems. And I heard the same thing
three times and it made me feel like,
"Okay, I'm going to solve it the third
time in the same way that I have before,
which is like in a one-on-one I'll bring
it up and I'll I'll be a coach or I'll
provide some resources for the person to
fix this. But like there's an underlying
problem, right? Which is like there's
not enough like self-learning of skills
that are necessary as we grow. Like
where is that coming from? That's it,
right? It's like I just I might have
waited in another world I might have
waited until like
much longer to realize that I needed to
go to the next level, which is like a
more formalized
like set of classes on specific topics
for for my managers. Now I know that's
something I should probably do like in
the next 12 months as opposed to, you
know, waiting two years, which is my
initial kind of
mentality for it.
Um
Yeah. Was it broken? No. Like was I
totally capable in one-on-ones of of of
coaching and getting people to think
about things better? Yes, but, you know,
um I think it suggested to me that that
there was there was this dimension where
we we needed to step up because people
had problems that they weren't
necessarily fully equipped to to face.
In episode 306, managing the
unmanageable with Ron Lichty, he
mentioned that it's
pretty much the the state of the art
today that companies don't have training
for their managers. In fact, like he's
he said, "Raise your hand if you are a
manager and if you had training the
first day you started." And pretty much
nobody had. You said that you expected a
certain level of self-learning for the
managers, but that you realized that you
needed some systematized way of training
them. What was the the steps that you
took to get there?
Well, so I haven't taken them, right?
You know what I mean? Like you this is
the exa- this is an example of a place
where I feel like I need to put that in
place. Like it's important. Generally at
smaller companies like the maturity
would be around coaching, right? So you
so generally like someone encounters
problem, is there somebody with more
experience that can coach them to solve
it, right? And that I think that's very
true for like a kind of management world
as well. So, you know, one of my
managers is like a hiring So, they're
they're they're they're they've become a
hiring manager. They've encountered a a
candidate with that they kind of can't
type they haven't encountered before.
They don't even They don't know how to
create an interview loop for it, right?
Cuz it's like a new kind of candidate
role that they're doing. Okay, I can
coach and help them to do that. But at
some point, that's going to happen like
enough in the org that we should just
like systematize like, "Hey, how do you
create new interview loops?" Right? I'm
not saying that's the like most
important thing that's that's that's
coming up right now.
Johnny, you would just get an external
coach, right? Cuz that The external
coach would be someone with much more
experience that's not in the org, so
they're not, you know, they have a they
have an independent kind of viewpoint on
things, and that should do that should
do most of it. But if you realize it's
systemic, then yeah, you should totally
do training. I I you know, on that
episode, I think I I agree that it's
There are not a lot of companies where
the day you become an
E M like you go through like a formal
like training immediately, but I mean,
for sure at, you know, companies of of
500 plus, there's a
I mean, a lot that I know, there
actually is like a like a a framework
for learning how do you manage
execution, how do you manage people and
grow a team, how do you recruit, how do
you set culture, how do you create
strategy, how do you create narratives,
right? And they're like space classes
through the time. But that's like a
pretty common practice I think today. I
I think of it as a best practice among
among companies. I just didn't think it
was something I would invest in until,
you know, we were like 200.
But now I see value in it. And it
doesn't, you know, that's just like
That's just the one example. So, I think
there is like a historically you know,
the
And I say historically, I say like maybe
10 years ago maybe that there's I always
think of like early Google where like
tech leads would become managers and
they had this the role the TLM role, and
I think management wasn't seen
necessarily as much as a separate skill
set, but I In my experience, that's not
that's not the reality of I guess best
in class among among your startups like,
you know, places like like Plaid I
think, but like Stripe and and Dropbox
take management training, uh
and evaluation based on like managing
ability, not just, you know, technical
contribution, like very seriously.
Let's talk a little bit about how the
engineering organization is set up from
a management perspective. How do you set
things up for success in terms of
um engineering maturity? What are the
the main steps that you take?
It's a very broad question, right? Cuz
we do like 80 things, right? So, like an
example, like a very concrete example
from right now, is we're in the process
of ramping up some of our SLAs across
all teams. Right? So, this is like
uptime, reliability, latency. We've had
those where we're we're ratcheting it
up. What they look like, which is just
part of, you know, being more mature as
a team. It's like, you know, you add
nines and you lower latency and you kind
of push people have better playbooks and
more uptime and spend less time on on
keeping systems up. So,
one part of that that's been interesting
for us is like how engineering and
support work together and how we kind of
provide SLAs on turnaround time for
support tickets. And I think something
that was not in the framework before
that I think I would now add and would
think much more seriously about uh is
like around common tooling being part of
uh what it means to be more mature. So,
kind of we we started on the journey
with some of the support stuff and and
like just different teams did it
differently. Even though the SLA
definitions were the same, right? The
way like communication happened, the way
you kept stats on whether you were
within SLA with
you know, with support, it was just done
differently. And then we were like,
"Well, that's stupid, right? You should
just have a common tool that holds
everybody accountable like in the same
way." Um even though different teams
might actually have different SLAs, it's
like it's all measured the same way and
whatnot. And I thought I thought that
was an interesting learning and it it it
kind of it got me thinking about the
kind of a
a lot of the maturity stuff because by
definition you wanted to apply across
many different teams, it's not
necessarily just about words on a piece
of paper about what what's your level
and what's the next level, right? It's
also about how do you make that
naturally happen? Like how do you make
people want to align across teams? And
so I think you know, it's it little
things like dashboards or tools that can
be used by multiple teams go a long way.
And so that made me think like well
actually maybe a dimension of of
maturity for an org is is like actually
having a tools team that's effective at
doing that, right? Not seeing the tools
team as a as something that you need
just because you you you need tooling to
exist, but seeing like a tooling team
like a core part of what it means to
drive up the maturity of your org. I
haven't like taken that thought to its
natural conclusion, but I think the more
I think about it, the more I see the
common tooling is like a thread that's
allowed yeah, people to be more mature.
And and like the the word common is the
most important one. It's like if
everybody uses the same measure for how
much time do they spend keeping systems
up versus improving the systems,
then if you have that measure the same
everywhere, then you can start saying
like well which teams relatively
speaking are spending too much time
keeping systems up, which is a sure sign
that the systems aren't as mature as
they need to be, right? And then once
you have a common definition like that
just comes to the fore of the org.
Whereas before you're just guessing. And
tooling's a big part of that, right?
Because tooling is what you what you
need to be able to measure these things
in the same way or or make it really
easy for for people to measure. Like an
another example right now is a like
incident response is another thing where
where we're we're kind of standardizing
a lot and I had to just before I had to
just like hey, we need an incident
response like at the next level of
maturity you have you have that super
well defined.
And then you know, then you you tell
people to do it and and and someone like
you know, manager goes and does the
research and comes up with an incident
response playbook and then you realize
wait, hold on a second like there's all
these steps. You have to create a slack
channel and email channel and these
people have to be notified and all that
and I was like, what if what if the
tools team actually just built that? You
know, if they just built a thing where
you just go to a page and you're like
create incident. And depending on the
level of incident, it just magically
created the channels and and email the
people and categorizes the Jira tickets
and like did all the things that you
needed. Well, then oh, suddenly like now
everyone is going to use that and like
every team's naturally going to have a
good incident response capability
because you're kind of like creating it
for them. I don't know if that's exactly
what you meant but that's like that's a
current instance where there's the the
tooling dimension I don't think is was
that obvious to me from from my
experience with this in the past.
Mostly I think is it was just done for
me. Like you know, I I think I just
never had to be in a position where
where I had to make that part of the
approach quite explicitly.
You said that like one one of the tools
you had was to track the SLA. Could you
explain what that means and maybe we can
go into that example a little bit more
and just I I think it illustrates pretty
well
your point about tooling providing a
consistent view of maturity across the
organization.
Yeah, I mean an SLA is kind of a service
level agreement. It's a it's an
agreement between generally a a team and
a service that it owns and an external
state stakeholder about the uptime and
performance characteristics and and
maybe other characteristics of of a
system. So, you might tell people that
hey, this service is going to be up 99%
of the time.
And then they know it's going to be down
1% of the time. That would be a bad SLA
but oh well, it would be a bad SLA if
you're providing a service
that people rely on but um so you have
that, right? And and and then there's a
question like okay, well, how do you
define uptime?
Well, there's actually a bunch of
different ways to to define uptime,
right? And so if you if you're just
telling teams like hey, have SLAs, then
one team will define uptime as a service
is up if
uh for a 5-minute window, 90% of
requests are successful. But, another
team might define it as a service is up
is for a 1-minute window, 95% of
requests go through. You'll just have
like very you have different
definitions. And maybe the just
thresholds are different, so the times
are different. But, for uptime, it's
like pretty easy. But, then for latency,
maybe it's a little harder. And as you
go down the list of things you want to
measure as part of your SLA, you're
going to have pretty different
uh definitions. So,
what you can solve this is
to just have
one team, generally this would be your
platform SRE team, in its
in the container or whatever whatever
you're using to to to launch and kind of
orchestrate and monitor live services,
just pre-build
like health checks that align with your
SLA. So, that at least whenever anyone's
building any new service now, they don't
have to build any dashboards, they don't
have to measure anything different. At
the very least, they get like a
definition of of a subset of SLA that's
consistent across the org.
Um you get it for free. Right. Now, they
can still choose to change it, they can
add they can add metrics to look at, but
at least you you come you come with that
common core. And so, that that's an
example where like the maturity isn't
just having SLAs, right? It's having
common SLAs. And it's not just having
common SLAs, it's like provide tooling
so that it's trivial for everybody to
have a a
a common SLA. And those are actually the
maturity levels that you would have,
right? You would start with just having
SLAs, and then you would have common
SLAs, and then you would have tooling
that makes SLAs like automatic for every
service. That's like the the kind of
mentality that that that that that I
think works really well. Um and there's
there's a bunch of other things like
that, right? Like testing coverage is
another one. Like do you if you use
different languages at your company,
like you're going to have different ways
to think about your testing coverage.
And then some teams will just ignore it,
and other teams will pay attention to
it. But, if you build tooling around
measuring the testing coverage, and you
make it part of the code review process,
so that uh when you do a pull request,
before it's accepted, literally the
reviewer can see the delta in the code
code code coverage that you have. And
like no one has to think about this. It
happens, it just happens automatically.
Then magically, like code coverage will
go up. Right? And so, you you will again
like in in your maturity map, you'll
have a certain level of a of a system
where you say, "Hey, uh for code
coverage, uh it doesn't matter." And
then you say, "It matters." And then you
say, "We have common definitions." And
then eventually you can say like you
you're you're your PR won't be accepted
if you didn't make the coverage go up. I
mean, that's pretty draconian, but you
know, it take that one with a grain of
salt. But, you know, you could you could
you could you could you could dream of
that one day. Um and so, for all these
things, right? It's like whoever's
building
you're taking it from a team-by-team
problem to like a common problem of some
common infrastructure that has to be
built. But, the truth is that in and of
itself is a maturity level. Like,
there's some point where org is big
enough where like by definition to be
mature you need the common tooling. I
don't think it's what you do when you
have like 20 engineers. When you're 20
engineers, just focus on like having,
you know, smoke tests, and you know,
make sure like some basic thing. But,
yeah, the tooling dimension I think is
is something that definitely at our
size, you know, 70 engineers, 200 people
total, becomes more and more important
in a way that I hadn't um at least
consciously realized.
At the company or organizational level,
the maturity would be based on how you
defined
one of these indicators. Like, let's say
it was testing.
You you you you ran through the
examples. So,
testing doesn't matter, testing does
matter. You had kind of a a common uh
framework, and then it was you have a
criteria you potentially reject uh pull
request if it if the test don't pass.
That's the organizational level, but
then at the team level, presumably it
would be how well were they doing like
with testing at whatever if the
organization level requirement was was
one thing like let's say the
organizational level requirement was
you have tests how well are they doing
based on that criteria.
Is at the org level you you literally
just have the ladder you could say we
want everybody of the org to be L4 for
testing you could say that. I think it's
more like each team can then ask
themselves like
where am I on testing? Right? And then
as soon as you've got the common measure
some teams are going to be like oh my
god coverage is 10% like it's a disaster
right? And then they're going to be like
well this is everybody knows that we're
we're like level two on the testing
scale like let's let's ramp that up.
That's the broad idea behind behind the
approach right and then they're
incentivized themselves to want to go
up. Um for sure like once you have extra
like on the SLA example you have
external customers you have SLAs with
the external customers everybody who can
possibly
like lower that SLA needs to be involved
with it and that's like an organization
wide thing but that's that's a little
bit different than engineering maturity
right because not everything in an
engineering maturity naturally impacts
like an outside customer directly like
often it's more it's more indirect
right? You could have you could you
could be up all the time without on-call
support by just like having people being
paged at any time of the day and like
jumping on the problem and fixing it
right? There's like
is is that's a pretty tiring approach
over time and people are going to burn
out right? It's much easier to do if you
know you you only alert when it's really
important if you have specific on-call
and all those things. So there's they're
not as tied as as as you would think.
Is there anything that we didn't cover
about engineering maturity that you
wanted to talk about?
I worked with a a security engineer a
long time ago we were talking about
security and and and people in very
smart engineers making silly security
mistakes and and I was like well we need
to educate the engineers into how you do
security. And he was like, you're wrong.
What you do is you provide them
libraries where if they just do the
things they normally do as engineers,
the security is taken care of for them.
And that is like a that is a powerful
insight, right? Cuz it means if you have
internally at your at your company, you
have a networking library that every
everybody needs to use, if you make a
version of that library that just takes
security, then then no one will make
security mistakes. And I think the same
thing is is true for the the tools. If
you If you make tools that naturally
align different teams and like push the
culture up to be more mature by either
measuring things or making clear when
things aren't mature, then people will
want to do their best work, right?
They'll want to step up and adhere to
that. And that's a super powerful idea.
Probably the best way to communicate
this is to actually write up some public
version of the framework and share it a
little bit like some companies have made
their level maps public uh
to help kind of other people build level
maps for for career progression
purposes. There's probably some common
version of this that just would be
informative for people to look at uh so
they could see at least for some
companies what it might mean, you know,
to be more mature on the testing
dimension or
the uptime dimension or the recruiting
dimension or whatnot. And
yeah. So, if there's one if there's one
takeaway for me is like I should
probably write some version of that up
to get these thoughts to be a little
more explorable
um than they might be just with words.
I think the main point for me is like
visibility about these things has just
adds a lot of value because it means
there's a common framework for people to
think about not just business impact,
which is generally what companies focus
a lot on, like what's the impact of of
the work, but also like,
you know, how good are engineering
practices and like what comes next. Um
so, to the I just want to repeat that
point cuz I think it's it's really
really important and and people
people forget the importance of building
like a common language, common tooling,
and a common understanding of like where
our works are going, not just not just
projects. And if you're a fast-growing
company, you know, your people and your
ability of your org to like tackle
problems, that determines how successful
you're going to be to a large extent.
Jean Deny, I think our listeners would
be very interested to read more about
your framework when you do write it up.
So, where can they go to follow you or
find out more about what you're doing?
I would say go to the Plaid blog and
if I have a busy enough holiday season,
hopefully something can go out on there
in in January, February.
And just incidentally, if anybody out
there just is interested to learn more
out of
more about Plaid, I would really suggest
like the website, the blog,
blog.plaid.com.
We're doing super well. We're have like
a huge 2019 ahead of us. So, kind of
really excited to get people to kind of
learn about the company and if their
listeners were excited to work here, we
are we are hiring all of the engineers,
PMs, designers,
support, etc. Never mind go-to-market or
ops
to keep being successful for many years.
We'll include links to those websites in
the show notes.
Cool. Thanks again, Jean Deny. It's been
It's been great having you on.
Likewise. Thank you so much, Nate.
For Software Engineering Radio, this has
been Nate Black. Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
se-radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.